You literally got rejected and you said
no. Look at it again. Last month, a
student group that I used to be a part
of at UCLA reached out asking if I
wanted to give a talk. I've had five
interns at Meta. When I think about the
ones that were rock stars, they had
the Hey everyone, welcome back to the
channel. My name is Ryan and if you're
new here, I try to share conversations
on this channel with more senior
software engineers so that you can learn
from their stories and their experience.
There is so much that no one told me in
college that I wanted to share with
these students. And so I enlisted some
help from my friend Ricky. You know, my
way is usually right and I make a bunch
of money and they're like, "Okay,
actually." We hosted a Q&A style event
and we received hundreds of questions,
some of which I really didn't expect to
see. How do you make as much money as
possible? I would say and others I
expected to see, but hopefully our
personal stories were helpful. So, I
feel like Ryan scammed me because I got
really lucky and I got all the offers at
every place I interviewed at except for
one. Like my mom, she was my hater. She
believed I wouldn't succeed without an
MBA. Here is the full
video. Excited to be here, everyone. My
name's Ryan. When Ashley reached out, I
was excited to talk to you all because I
feel like there's so many things that we
learned in industry that no one tells
you until you actually fail and you get
into industry. And I'm hoping that we
can tell you a lot of that today. Um, do
you want to introduce? Yeah. Hey, I'm
Ricky. Uh, really excited to be here,
too. I feel like um, so much of my
success postgrad is from everything that
I learned at UCLA and all the people
that I've met. So really excited to be
here and kind of give back. Before we
get started, when I right before I got
into industry, I knew nothing about the
levels. And so like what even is staff?
Like when I got promoted to staff, my
parents thought it was lower than
senior. So u it doesn't sound that good.
So this is just to give you a little
idea. This is like levels.fy. Of course,
when you get promoted, you make more
money, but also I feel like your work
becomes a lot more interesting because
it becomes higher level, more impactful,
and it's a lot more satisfying. I'm just
showing this to you so that when we say
junior, mid-level, senior staff in this
talk, you know, um what it means and
like what it refers to. So, I'll give
you a little bit of a explanation of
what each level means, right? Because
you look at it and you're like, you
know, what does it actually mean? So at
the junior level, so this is usually
where new grads are right here. The
expectation is just for you to be able
to kind of code and um you know push out
some stuff with a decent amount of help.
Whereas once you get to the mid level,
there's an expectation that yes, now you
can kind of do more do more things on
your own, but you still need help here
and there. And usually from junior to
midle I think on average it takes people
maybe two to 3 to four years and then
from mid-level to senior at the senior
level. So we say that senior level is
terminal because a lot of people will
get to senior and just stop. So there's
usually no expectation to go beyond
senior. It's more like do you want to
but there is an expectation for you to
go from junior to mid-level to senior.
So mid-level to senior takes around
maybe also like 2 3 4 years. At the
senior level, the expectation is that
someone will give you a tax and you can
kind of finish it on your own and you
don't need that much help. And then at
the staff level, so again, this is if
you actually want to get to that level,
it's a lot more responsibilities. Some
people say that, you know, it's not even
worth the pay increase because you
probably uh have to work a lot more in
terms of your, you know, your hourly
wage, right? Like how much you make per
hour. Uh but at this level the
expectation is that you're setting the
strategy for the team. You're really
thinking about the direction that the
team should go in and you're kind of
leading all the you know senior
mid-level junior folks. So hopefully
that was helpful. Um I thought you know
I had no clue what all of these things
were when I first started at Google. So
you know hopefully this gives you a
better view of what all the levels mean.
Uh I was wondering is it true at Google
that terminal level is actually L4? cuz
I've heard that somewhere. I wasn't uh
with time not really. Um so there
definitely is more and more of an
expectation that you can eventually get
this senior but I think other companies
um are more aggressive. So up other
companies often have a policy called up
or out. So if you aren't able to get to
that level then bye-bye. Um
but but I think at Google at least it's
a little bit more relaxed and it's not
as aggressive of a policy. Yeah. Yeah.
And the up and out policies by the way
they're not meant to be intense and
scary like 90 I don't have the exact you
know data but it's like 90 plus%
probably um you know make it to those
levels. So it's actually kind of like uh
I guess an upper bound of how quickly
you'll grow. Go ahead, Bill. What's
what's the mix of uh of technical and
supervisory responsibilities that you
have as you're going up those levels? I
see. I mean, on a high level, like
junior, people are handing you tasks,
you're doing them with a lot of help.
Mid level, you're not being watched on
how you do it, but people are still
giving you things to do. Senior people
tell you there's an area that needs your
help, and you go and create the tasks,
and you do them. and staff is you find
the areas that need things to be done.
That's like the high level. How accurate
is levels? FYI, sorry during this. It's
pretty accurate except the fluctuations
in the equity. That's actually Yeah. So,
I just pulled these numbers today. The
Meta's numbers on the left, like why are
they so much higher than Google's? Well,
Meta stock has been like ripping
recently, so like like that's why. But
generally, it it's pretty it's pretty
accurate. So yeah, let's get into some
of the prepared questions. Before we got
here today, you know, in the RSVP,
there's the ability for you to submit
questions. We'll go through those and
we'll kind of answer with various
stories. Maybe Ashley, you can MC. A lot
of people in the audience have
internship plans and we're all wondering
how do we succeed as an intern. The
rubric at different companies, it
fluctuates slightly, but it's somewhat
similar. When you get into that
internship, they're going to give you a
project and they're going to see how
quickly you can get the project done. If
you can do that project in half of your
internship's time, obviously that's
going to be really good. So, they're
going to be measuring your productivity.
That's a big part of it. Another thing
is the quality of your work. And you can
measure that by how many times your code
needs to be reviewed until it's
submittable. So at the beginning of the
internship you write code and then it's
trash and it needs to be reviewed many
many times because you don't know the
code base yet. But ideally by the end of
the internship your code should be
reviewed with nits and landing with one
or zero revisions. So that should be
changing. And then lastly you should be
communicating and um you know pushing
like after you finish that project what
is that thing that you do afterwards? if
you propose improvements on top of your
project, maybe you propose a new project
entirely like that that's like a really
strong internship performance. And so
that was that was a lot. That's pretty
intense, but that's what it looks like
if you want to really crush it and for
sure get I would say I definitely agree
like most of the time internship
projects should be pretty well scoped
like there's kind of a defined end. So
that's not usually true more at the
higher levels when you know when you're
a full-time employee. the problems are a
little bit more ambiguous, the solutions
a little bit more ambiguous, but usually
as an intern, they're I feel like
they're really just trying to see if you
can like, you know, do some basic
coding, kind of finish a basic task. But
your your project was actually not like
that, right? Tell that story. Maybe it
can help some people if they Yeah. So
during my junior year um my internship
was at Google and my internship I only
wrote 800 lines of code which is really
low and I was really stressed out
because I looked at my peers you know my
other UCLA friends that were Google
interns. I was halfway through the
internship and I had submitted like 300
lines of code and I look at my friend
and they've submitted 11k lines of code
and I'm like oh Um but in the end
it was fine and the reason was because
um while lines of code is definitely you
know part of the metrics that people
might use to evaluate your productivity
they also look at other things. So for
me I really um took a lot of time trying
to understand the codebase. I wrote a
really complex design doc that explored
a lot of pros and cons of different
approaches. So the design itself was
very technical and that's how I was able
to show my productivity and that I was
able to kind of find a solution to this
um problem at work. You know even though
I at the end of my internship I still
only wrote n 800 900 lines of code I did
get a return offer. It was really nice.
So that's kind of what happened in my
internship. Next questions after we
hopefully all get our return offers and
we're working full-time. We're all
wondering how do you be successful and
how do we get promoted? So, how did you
guys get promoted so quickly to staff
engineer in your 20s? You know, going
back to the levels that we saw earlier,
right? We had junior, mid-level, senior,
staff. So, at each level, you get to
kind of a steady state where you're able
to do well at that level, right? But if
you want to get to the next level, you
really need to be thinking about what
exactly does a next level project look
like? How do I start acting like the
next level, right? Let's say you were a
junior level and you were super
productive. You did a bunch of junior
level projects. That is not enough to
get to the mid-level because you have
not been able to demonstrate that you
can do a mid-level project. So, what is
actually more impactful is for you to
do, you know, one mid-level project that
solidly solidly shows that you're at
that level. So, I think what Ryan and I
probably did really well is that we were
really able to think about what is the
next level project? How can I do it and
how can I get there? So, we were really
focused on making sure that we weren't
spending too much time on projects that
wouldn't necessarily get us to the next
level. You'll hear this key word, your
manager will probably say it a lot,
which is uh behaviors, which is that the
things that get you promoted is not just
doing a ton of work at your current
level. Like I say, you're junior
engineer, you do 10 times as many
features as a junior engineer. That will
get you a really good rating. Your
performance review will be good. But
when your manager is looking to fill out
like a the rubric for the next level for
instance, none of the things will be
checked off. There's nothing about, you
know, initiative or doing anything
that's expected of the mid level. So
like the thing that gets you promoted
quickly is really understanding the next
level's behaviors and going and taking
initiative and finding projects that fit
that. Um, and so I remember when I was
like, you know, I was really really
eager to get promoted and so I was
constantly talking to my manager like,
you know, as soon as I got promoted to
one level, I was like, "Okay, what's
what's the next level? What what can I
do?" Maybe that was annoying for my
manager, but he was really helpful in
teaching me what were the things that I
needed to pick up so I could continue to
pick up next level opportunities. And I
think that's a big part of why my
promotions were as fast as they were.
Next question. How much of your success
in software engineering and getting
promotions is just luck? Although luck
is a big part of it, you can actually do
things to increase your luck. When I
think back to a lot of the projects and
things that got me promoted, there was
some level of initiative where I went
out of my way to find something. I'll
give you an example like actually, you
know, actually when I graduated UCLA, I
went to Amazon and I was floundering
like I was not doing well at all. But
after I was there for like eight months,
I realized like this is I'm not
learning. I don't know what the growth
to the next level looks like. And so I
just took matters into my own hands and
you know applied to a bunch of different
places. I got really lucky and I got all
the offers at every place I interviewed
at except for one which if you're
curious what that place is that rejected
me, maybe I can tell you off camera
later. But um you know like I ended up
getting to Meta and that kind of like
set up my career for the rest and you
could say that it was lucky that I got
the interview but also you know I
grinded to like you know apply to all
the places grinded leak code and like
that really increased my luck. A good
part of its luck no doubt but also you
have a lot of uh agency and so I think
that's you know really important too.
Definitely agree. I think um the way I
would frame it is that luck is two parts
right? One is the opportunity coming and
the other part is you being prepared for
that opportunity when it comes because
if you get an interview, right, that
could be luck, right? Maybe you talk to
the right person at the career fair and
they're like, "Oh, you know, why not?"
You know, and they give it to you, but
you're not prepared, right? You're not
like studying and preparing for the
interview and then that opportunity is
going to pass you by. And I feel like
that is really true, you know, not just
when you're finding a job, but also at
work. And in Ryan's case, right, he is
setting himself up for more
opportunities by leaving Amazon. Um, and
of course, like he was prepared um and
ready when those opportunities came to
him. If you had one piece of advice to
give us, what would it be? I love this
question cuz I a lot of people have
asked me this and if if you don't take
anything from today's talk, I hope at
least you take this part. I would say
that the one piece of advice is to ask
tons of questions. Keep asking questions
when you're at work. I mentored a lot of
interns. And one intern mentee I had,
she at the beginning of her internship,
she asked me, you know, Ricky, if you
had one thing, one piece of advice, what
would be? And I told her, ask questions,
keep asking questions, keep asking
questions. And at the end of her
internship, I asked her, okay, so is
there anything you wish I told you at
the beginning of your internship? And
she was like, I wish you told me to ask
questions. And I was like, "No, no, no.
I definitely told you that. I that's I'm
100% sure I told you that." And she told
me, "Yeah, Ricky, you did, but like you
didn't mean it." You know, I really want
to emphasize it to you. So, I think a
lot of people, you know, me included,
when we start at work, we're like
nervous and a little bit scared. And for
me, I thought if I ask too many
questions, they're going to think I'm
stupid, right? Uh, but I ended up kind
of like trying to be, you know,
delusional as possible and just being
like, "Okay, you know, I deserve to be
here. Like, I have to ask questions."
And I also kept trying to remind myself
that it's better to ask questions and
learn and for them to think you're
stupid than to not ask questions. Never
learn anything, you know, and stay dumb,
right? I also remember thinking like,
I'm just going to try to learn as much
as I can here and if I get fired, I get
fired, but at least I learned. So,
definitely try to ask a lot of
questions. I think you know I have
mentored and grown a lot of engineers
and what I think is the biggest
differentiator between those that like
really succeed really quickly and the
ones that don't is how quickly they're
able to start asking questions,
learning, being curious, unblocking
themselves and really taking that
initiative to figure things out. One
thing I can add to that is I've had five
interns at Meta and some of them were
rock stars, some of them were not. When
I think about the ones that were rock
stars, they had the the audacity to
propose improvements. Even though
obviously I'm the more senior person,
they had the audacity to ask questions,
propose improvements. Sometimes they
weren't right, but I could see the
logic, but many times they were. And
when I think of the low performers, I
remember oftent times they were like
quieter. They kind of I didn't know
exactly what their progress was. I could
tell they were trying really hard to
figure things out without my help and
then time would pass, time would pass
and they're making no progress and then
you know at the end they're not going to
get a return offer. So asking question
especially when you're junior is is
really important. What if I feel like
I'm asking too many questions and I feel
like I'm not a good and bad.
So my perception really successful
software engineers were in college was
that they were just like the super
genius um you know they're probably the
ones setting the curve in the class in
my CS classes but that's actually not
true. Like I think what uh makes a
really good software engineer is having
a decent level of technical skills of
course but also having a decent level of
soft skills. you know, learning how to
persuade others, how to influence
others, because if you think about what
you're doing at work, it's like this
giant group project, right? And you
know, I'm sure you all have had group
projects and you probably also had
tension at times in the group project,
right? You want it, you want things to
be done this way, but this other person
is like, "No." And at work, if you just
tell, you know, whoever you disagree
with, like your idea is trash. You know,
we should do it my way, they're not
going to listen to you, right? So, a
better way to kind of communicate that
message is, hey, you know, I see that
you're pretty frustrated. You know, I
see your point of view and why you would
want this solution. Perhaps we can
compromise and find um, you know,
negotiate like some in between or some
middle ground. What do you think? They
are much more willing to buy into your
idea and you're ultimately able to kind
of ship things and get things launched.
Um, and that is, you know, I would say
just as important as being a really
great coder and understanding the
technical parts. Yeah, definitely. I
think one thing that surprised me, which
I never thought would be true until I
got to the industry, was that how little
of the job was actually the code. So,
uh, code is is really important, too. So
they're both important, but I think when
you get into the industry, you'll see
there's all this other stuff around the
code that matters a lot. Obviously, the
people are important because it is kind
of like a giant collaborative project.
Like there's thousands of engineers
working on this software. Um, but
there's all these other things too, like
you have to write a ton. Like I hated
writing in high school. Felt like not
objective, like not as I don't know. I
just didn't like writing. Um but when I
got into industry like I realized
writing is the job. It's how you
influence others. Every code change has
all this writing around it. Like you got
to write design doc before you start you
know get feedback. Then when you
actually writing the code you write a
description of the code. Then when you
land it and it has results you write
results. You write about the results and
you know share that with the group. So
there's there's so much around the code
that you need to do that's about people
and communication and I think if you're
not is is this a common term gigachad
gigachad coder if you're not a gigachad
coder you should be fine I think
everyone in this room if you go to UCLA
you're smart enough to be writing code
that matters and then a lot of what's
going to make you excel is actually not
about the code and your technical skills
related to that have you guys ever
gotten imposttor syndrome? Imposter
syndrome. My best friend been with me my
whole career. So I think a lot of people
get imposter syndrome. I think it's very
normal. I think a majority of people
actually do get imposter syndrome. And I
think it's a little bit odd too because
I remember when I first joined Google,
right? I passed the interviews, I did my
internship, they gave me a passing grade
on my internship and then I got there
and I was like, "Oh shit." you know,
like everyone everyone look everyone's
gig Chad Coder here. Um, how am I going
to make it? Surprisingly, even after I
got promoted, after I got promoted, I
was still like, uh, maybe like they
promoted me wrong. Like maybe I got
promoted too early. And then after I got
promoted after that, I was like, oh man,
this well maybe not the last promotion,
maybe they like screwed up this
promotion. And I had it a lot um during
my career. And you know, it's pretty
normal, right? Um, the best way I kind
of got around it is, you know, again
going back to that mindset of all right,
even if I'm like not meant to be here,
like let's try to learn as much as I
can, do the best job I can, and you
know, if I get fired, then at least I
learned a lot. But, you know, I never
got fired luckily. Uh, but impositive
syndrome definitely still comes here and
then in waves too. Um, but you know, I
think eventually uh you get over it and
everyone it's really an experience that
a lot of people have. So don't feel
stressed out if you ever feel that way
at work. Did you ever have any feedback
that made you feel because you must have
been Yeah. just getting good marks. Like
how do you how's it possible that you
felt not good even though you were
getting all this praise? I was just an
anxious little kid, you know? I was I
was just always stressed out about work.
And I remember one time in a one-on-one
with my manager, you know, he like
looked at me a little bit and he was
like, "You need to chill, you know, like
you're doing okay, you know, calm down."
And I was like, are you sure though?
Like, you know, seems sus.
Um, I think part of it was also because,
you know, when they say you're doing
well, I'm like, I was, but is this like
a C passing doing well or is this like a
A+ doing well? You know, like and I
think eventually I did kind of learn um,
you know, through talking with my
manager and understanding the
expectations for myself of like kind of
how I was doing and I was a little bit
less stressed after that. But yeah, I
was pretty stressed in the beginning.
How do you advocate for yourself while
at work? This will be helpful for your
whole career, but if you're also going
into internship, this could be helpful.
In order to get promoted, there's kind
of like two pieces to it. One is you do
good work. That's obvious. Like we all
know do good work, you're going to get
promoted. But actually, promotions are
ultimately decided by people. They need
to know about your work. And if you go
and build this amazing feature that
nobody knows about, doesn't matter how
good it is, no, you're not going to get
any recognition for it. And so, you
know, how do you advocate for yourself
after you've done great work, which is
the hard part? There's just this last
step that you got to do this last few%
of your time where you maybe you either
write about it or you present it in a
meeting or something like that where you
say, "Hey, hey everyone." Let's say
you're at an internship. You have your
intern project. you hit a big milestone
rather than just like quietly moving on
to the next step. Maybe in your
one-on-one you tell your intern manager
like, "Hey, I did it and it's like a few
weeks early. I'm ready for the next
thing." Like that kind of puts the thing
in the idea in their head. Also, maybe
you make a post internally. You write an
email or something that says like, "Hey,
you know, update on my project. It's
done. I'm I'm killing it. Look, all the
good results here." and you can write
about it in a way that uh matters to to
the audience. If you do that, people are
going to get a sense of, okay, this
person's killing it. And it will be kind
of surprising if you didn't get a uh a
return offer if you were doing so well
and people knew that you were doing
well. So, this is like specifically that
last step, and I think a lot of people
miss this, especially if they're more
introverted or they're more quiet, is
taking that last step on after the good
work. You got to tell everyone about it.
And writing is one of the best ways to
do it, but maybe, you know, it depends
on your specific team setup. Maybe you
can talk about the work in standup or,
you know, whatever meeting. The term
that we often use at work is visibility.
So, you want to have visibility for
yourself. It could be doing it by
yourself as Ryan said, but it can also
be doing it through other means like
through your manager or through, you
know, whoever else you're working with
like a PM. Um, they can also help you
get visibility, but it is really
important. I forgot, but there's some
analogy where it's like, oh, you know,
if a tree falls in a forest and no one
sees it, did it really fall? So, I also
think I have to think about that, you
know, like just because you did a
project, people you also need to get
people to know that you did that
project, right? Um otherwise in the
future like you're trying to get
promoted and you're like oh I did this
and you know whoever is helping you get
promoted is like no one knows like how
how is anyone supposed to know? Uh so
it's definitely important to get
visibility for yourself at work. So I
think a lot of people are interested in
this postcribe which is better tech or
startups.
Yeah. Okay. Actually I'm curious what
what do you guys think? Okay. So between
big tech versus startups, if you had
both options, if you would pick big
tech, raise your
hand. Okay, that's like the whole
room. Okay. And then anyone startups?
How about for startups? All right, we
got a few a few people. For anyone who's
going to or would want to go to a
startup, are you willing to answer why?
I'm kind of curious. I'm a first movers
revive. So like if the cup pig gets
really big, you'll have a lot of
that you fail, but it always go work for
big tech. Yeah, I see another hand
raised. Yeah, whoever changes you might
like more fun facing and like might make
more of an impact like proportional to
the company. Yeah, because I think the
impact is probably going to be smaller
because of the scale of big tech, but
proportional to company it'll be bigger,
I'm sure. Yeah. Um Okay. Yeah, that's
that's really interesting. So, okay, big
tech versus startups. Um, before saying
like the answer that I would give, I
think there's some differences, right?
Like, you know, big tech versus
startups, one of the biggest things is
the prestige or like the some people
call it like brand equity. If you go to
a name that is known and then anyone
sees that resume, it's you're at least
that good. You're at least that bar. So
it makes it a lot easier to get hired.
So if you go to a startup that people
don't know, then you wouldn't have that
prestige. There's startups, there's a
whole range of startups, though. There
are very well-known startups, too. Like
imagine a company like Perplexity or
something. Um, you know, that's a hot
startup. Maybe you would still get some
of that prestige. But I definitely
remember I went to Amazon, which was, I
guess, the lowest tier of the Fang ones
at the time. Probably still true. I
don't know. But um a after I I went
there like my LinkedIn was blowing up
and I was not writing on LinkedIn or
anything. Just so many recruiters just
coming in random emails. So I do think
that's worth something for sure. The the
first mover advantage that's
interesting. One thing that I'll say is
generally true for big tech versus
startups across career growth across
your compensation is it's a trade-off
between high expected value versus high
variance. So what I mean by that is um
if you go to big tech you're in the
average case you're probably going to be
doing better but you will never have a
moon up or a moon down scenario. So if
you wanted to like you know the jobs we
work today will never be like rich rich
rich like you I mean you'll make a good
amount. You make a good amount. It it's
it's it's a good amount. I'm very happy.
No no it's great but like you want like
$10 million or something. You're not
going to get like that level of rich by
you know working in big tech. Whereas at
a startup you can you know boom or bust.
You could your company could be dead
tomorrow. you could also be, you know,
making, you know, eight figures or nine
figures in like some crazy cases if
you're a founder. So, and then that's
also true for your career. If you were
there early and it moons, you you'll be,
you know, like a director really fast.
You'll you'll go and like VP like some
crazy thing where, you know, you could
never do that in big tech. So, it it
kind of depends. Yeah. I personally
chose big tech. Um, like at the time I
had a couple of startup offers and I
also had a couple big tech
offers and honest part of the reason is
I'm just lazy. You know, I'm a good work
life balance. Like I sold my soul to
Google so that I could live a good life.
Um, so I'm so glad I chose big tech cuz
you know some of my friends they are at
startups. They're working so hard and in
some cases I think some of them did moon
you know go crazy and some of them did
not so crazy. And you know, I'm very
happy I chose big tech. Uh it's actually
really interesting because uh at UCLA,
it seems like there is there are a lot
of there's a big portion of people that
want to go into big tech much more than
other colleges. Um and I've always
wondered why because I've also talked to
some recruiters from startups and they
say, "Yeah, we always go to UCLA to
recruit uh but no one seems to want to
join so we kind of stop going." Which
colleges are the startup colleges?
You're talking, you know, like um
Stanford, I think. Um they said a lot of
Ivy ones, so I'm like, is it just
because you know, like they're rich, so
they don't need to make money
immediately after college? I don't know.
You know, these are just my
guesses. Yeah. Uh one last thing I would
say is the learnings can be different.
So in in big tech, you're learning from
the industry best practices that are
already set. So it's kind of like you're
not going to have a lot of variance.
You're going to get you're going to
learn the good stuff. Uh it's it's all
there like you know all the the best
practices in startups. It can vary
widely like your role could could be
even less code. It could be maybe more
PM stuff. It can be more a bunch of
things. Whatever the startup needs at
the moment depending on how small it is.
Yeah. I think it's I guess it's similar
to the variance thing. you could learn a
lot too from a crazy startup trajectory,
but also there can be a case where it
crashes and burns and you don't learn as
much. So, um, so yeah, I mean, you know,
in conclusion, I've I picked big tech
and I I would recommend big tech at
least for the first few years of your
career. You get just huge jump in
prestige. You just lock that in and then
you can do whatever you want after that.
just learn all the basics in big tech,
get that early signing bonus and then
you know rest of your life do you can go
you know do do whatever. And as interns
and as I guess future new grads how do
people managers like you guys measure by
impact? Impact is just another way of
saying the concrete measurable outcomes
of your work. And the tech industry is
great because you're not compensated or
rewarded based off of the time you spend
or like your years of experience. Like
literally, you know, how much money did
you make or how much you how much faster
did you make that important customer
flow or whatever whatever it is. And so
when we talk about impact, it's it's
specifically that. And so my answer to
this question would be it really depends
on the team you're on. If you're working
on ads, it's going to be money. If
you're working on some infrastructure
team and maybe it's the cost of the
database or maybe it's the latency of
the database. If you're working on like
a growth team, it might be like daily
active users or percentage of people
that sign up on some critical customer
flows. So, it really depends. I think
the main thing is like wherever you go,
you should 100% learn this from your
team and your manager because this is
how you're rewarded. Yeah. Like if you
write like 10k lines of code and it's
all fixing typos in the codebase,
there's no impact, right? Like you know,
I mean there's a little bit of impact,
the tiniest bit, but it's nothing
compared to, you know, for example, if
you were somehow able to 2x the revenue
of the company, right? That's that's
probably something that people care a
little bit more about. Yeah, like one
line code change that makes a 20%
improvement and something that matters
versus like hundreds of thousands of
lines doing random things no one cares
about. Always want the oneline change
and that's true pretty much at every
company. Do you need an MBA for
engineering management? Yeah. So, this
is an interesting question. I remember
when I was in college, I had the same
question cuz I didn't know. And I think
you just learn from maybe the older
generation that MBAs are good for some
reason. I I don't have an MBA. I'm a
manager. You don't have an NBA. You're a
manager. But actually, I was working on
some research with some company to like
answer this question. I actually have
this graph. It's kind of interesting.
So, this company basically scrapes
LinkedIn to pull data. And you can see
here they pulled like a few thousand
data points from LinkedIn about
directors and higher. And you can see
with and without MBA it's comp
comparable. Um and actually without MBA
is even lower. So yeah, you don't need
NBA. Yeah, it's really odd. Like my mom,
she she kept telling me to get an NBA.
Like I had to get an MBA and I didn't
understand why. But I think also it's
because like my mom's, you know, an
immigrant and she's like, "Ah, UCLA is
not good enough. me Ivy, you know, like
Stanford, you got to go Stanford. You
got to get an MBA at Stanford. Um, and
she she always like I don't know why she
was my hater. She would have she
believed I wouldn't succeed without an
MBA. Uh, now she's a little bit like uh
more chilled because uh I got the staff,
right? And then she's like looking on
Xiaoongu like little red book and she's
like, "Oh wait, that's kind of
good."
And I guess we're all suffering through
this right now. So, we're wondering for
you guys, how was college recruiting?
Definitely wanted to have a black hole
swallow me at times. Um, college
recruiting was definitely, you know,
hard. I'm sure all of y'all have um kind
of endured it. Um, I think one of my
recommendations or like a story I like
to share with y'all about my college
recruiting experience is with Yelp. So,
I had a I had a technical coding
challenge with Yelp, right? They sent me
I don't know. a hacker ring thing and I
opened it. I was doing C++ because you
know how we all learn C++ to start and
that's all I knew at the time. God
forbid and it was it was a merge step of
a merge sort, right? And I just had to
complete it and um like I did it I put
it together. I'm pretty sure the code
was right, but I was getting a seg fault
and I did not did not know why. I kept
track of my work and I really didn't get
understand why I was not able to compile
the code and it was a 15-minute coding
challenge and then I failed and you know
the Yelp recruiter came out um and I was
like okay Ricky so goodbye um and I
emailed her back and I say come on like
I knew this I knew this hacker rig it
was the mer of a merge sort tell your
engineer to look at it because I'm 100%
it's sure it's right and she did and she
said the engineer took a look at it it
looks correct actually Um, here's
another coding challenge to do again.
And that one I passed and I was able to
move on to the interview round. So, uh,
that was an example of me persevering
through college recruiting. So, you
know, it's worth it, uh, to kind of push
back sometimes and advocate your for
yourself during the college recruiting
process. Yeah, for your first role,
that's the hardest one. No doubt. You
have to be scrappy. like what you did
there like you you literally got
rejected and you said
no like look at it again and so you yeah
you kind of have to do stuff once you
get the first one it's a lot easier um
but yeah definitely want to be scrappy
and I think like yeah my first role was
like some random company um I don't even
put on my resume anymore but uh it
helped me get some experience so then
the next time I my resume looked a bit
better and then I could shoot some shots
of some better companies. Yeah, I think
it's tough the first one, but you know,
if you can get a little scrappy or like
take on some companies that are not as
desirable, that can help a lot. People's
number one
motivation, as much money as possible.
Yeah, this is interesting cuz I feel
like I didn't I had no idea about money
when I was in college. Like actually my
life goal at some point was like, oh, I
want to make 200K one day eventually.
And then I have some people. Yeah, I was
actually I was eating uh I was eating
lunch with uh Daniel and you were saying
you looked behind you and you're like,
"Oh, 200k is like minimum wage in the
Bay
Area." Um so yeah, but it's interesting
that you guys asked this. Um how do you
make as much money as possible? I would
say that it depends on how much money
you want to make. If you want to be rich
rich, then you don't do what Ricky and I
are doing. Um, yeah. If you want to be
truly rich, you probably go to big tech
for a few years and then you start your
own company because that that's like the
only way to make, you know, super crazy
amounts. I mean, would you say something
different or it's like if you want to be
like 50 mil rich, right? You probably
have to go crazy with something. you got
to, you know, join OpenAI as employee
number 50 and then you can probably make
it. Uh me and Ryan, maybe if we work
hard for another 20, 30, 40 years, uh
and we get promoted three more times,
yeah, maybe we could get there and, you
know, the stock market, whatever
continues to do well. Um, but if you're,
you know, if you're just having, if
you're just looking to have like a good
life and, you know, just buy, uh, the
things that you want and, you know, go
on vacation whenever you want, I would
say definitely go into big tech and just
do a good job there. Um, as me and Ryan
did. So, we have some last words for
you. Um, and what I would like to impart
with you guys is that work is not
everything. You know, like even though
we're here talking about our careers and
we look back at work careers and we're
very proud of what we did, when I look
back on my 20s, you know, now I'm in my
late 20s, I don't The happiest moments
for me were not when I was like working
all the time or when I was getting
promoted, right? The happiest times were
like when I'm at Coachella and I'm
really drunk and my shirt's off and I'm
having fun with my friends. Um, those
are the most memorable moments for me um
in my 20s, right? So, even though you
should work hard, right, and hopefully
you can do a good job at your job,
definitely make sure to also go have
fun. You're in tech. Um, you'll graduate
and then you'll have free will. I don't
know, go see a Beyonce or Taylor Swift
concert. Um, go travel if that's what
you want to do. But, uh, make sure
you're definitely a multiaceted person.
You're not just, you know, like if I
made Google my life and I got laid off,
you know, I'd probably be crashing out,
right? But if Google lays me off one
day, I'll be fine because I know I'm so
much more um than just, you know, some
computer science guy. So that's advice
that I want to impart with y'all. Yeah.
I mean on on that point too I guess one
another way to look at it is in every
aspect every area there's like this
general curve of like diminishing
returns
where if you put in a lot of extra stuff
into some area that little by little the
gains are going to go away and so
actually if you're truly a maximizer you
go everywhere where you can get more
returns before it starts to diminish so
I guess that could be another way to to
look at it as well. Um, but yeah, thanks
for for having us here. That's like the
prepared questions. If you guys have any
questions, too. We like let's get into
those two. We don't need to to end it
and we're happy to continue to answer,
but those are the end of the slides.
Yeah. So, we're going to open it up to
audience questions, I guess. Like, what
are your current goals like career or
likewise?
You seem like pretty successful. So,
like my story is funny. So, I feel like
Ryan scammed me because I actually feel
like in the beginning I was not that
career driven. Um, but then, you know,
Ryan and I were roommates. Uh, and we're
still roommates. And I feel like he
would kind of like whisper in my ear and
be like, "Oh, but what if we got
promoted, bro?" Like, "Wouldn't that be
dope?" And then I was like, "Oh, maybe I
guess." Um, and you know, but I'm really
thankful to Ryan, right? because uh I
think back in the t uh back in the day
when I saw these levels uh we also had
data about you know how long it took to
progress from each level right and I was
like oh you know I'll just take my time
kind of doing it but then Ryan I was
like ah but what if we went faster than
that um and I honestly didn't even think
that it was possible right so uh but
then I kind of asked my manager and my
manager was also supportive of me and
also kind of helped me and as she got
promoted download it a lot quicker than
average. I obviously tried, right? I
obviously put in the work.
Um, I I don't know how many of you guys
are from the Bay Area. He He's from the
barrier. He went to one of those intense
high schools. Well, he he says that I
tricked him. No, he has something inside
of him. He's pretty competitive. I'll
say grinding is kind of fun, but
uh do you guys know where Monavista is?
Oh my god. It's a Monav Vista kid right
here. But I've been trying to get the
motivista out of me. It was kind of
like, oh, why not, right? Like, if I'm
going to, if I can, like, why not try to
do it? So, I did put in the effort and I
did kind of succeed, but I wasn't I
definitely wasn't like, I don't know,
giving up all the other things in life
that I wanted to do just to kind of uh
continue on with my career. So, it seems
like you guys have stayed at your same
job for the most of your career uh at
least for now. And I'm wondering like
what you guys perspectives are on
switching jobs every two three years
with like for the money or for like more
responsibilities promotion. Yeah. So I
think I'm a really special case where
since I have joined Google I've been on
the same team and basically under the
same manager and I really have not
changed any teams. But that's not to say
that I haven't like looked for other
teams, right? I think what usually
happened is I would look around and I
would see that my grass is indeed
greener. So for me at least, I stayed on
the same team, but there's definitely
this aspect of survivorship bias, right?
Maybe other people on my team, they left
because they weren't having as good of a
time. So I think it really depends um
case by case. I definitely think it's
worth thinking about, you know, every
six months, do I still want to be here?
Are there still the right opportunities?
Does my team support me? does a manager
to support me? And you know, depending
on your answer to those questions, you
can think about leaving or staying.
Yeah, I I've done a lot of research on
this topic actually and it's it's kind
of interesting. It's a little bit
nuanced. So, uh actually maybe the level
thing. Oh, okay. So, actually job
hopping the common take you hear is like
job hop for promos, you know,
no-brainer. Do it. Actually, it really
depends. So like if you want optimal
career strategy, it would probably be
that you aggressively try to job hop in
this area while you're trying to get
promoted and you just take the faster
path because here like momentum does not
matter that much. You're just trying to
get to the next level. And so you know
if I were to put it simply, you probably
want to job hop in this area. But once
you get down here, job hopping is
actually counterproductive because first
off, you're not no one's going to hire
someone at E7 or L7. If you're an L6, it
just does not happen. If anything,
they're going to downlevel and you hire
you here. So, it's not going to be an
effective strategy. But also, a lot of
the promotions at this level come from
building credibility and trust and
having a track record. And so, if you're
just job hopping all the time, you're
not going to have that momentum. and
people are not going to know you. So, I
would say, you know, optimal is like
aggressively job hop, especially if
things aren't good. Just go to some
place that'll give you a promo if you
can get one. But then here, you got to
be a little more thoughtful. One last
thing I'll add, which is kind of
interesting, is I've seen I saw someone
job hop from E5 to E7. I also saw
someone drop hop from E5 to E6. And I
think the way that they did that was
really interesting. If you're in a
well-measured ladder like I am, you you
all know I'm right here and the
recruiters know that too. No one's going
to put me here. Uh at best they'll put
me here. But if you left here, like
let's say I left and I went to started
my own company. I'm I'm like in this
probability cloud somewhere, you know,
like no one knows what I am. And so then
you can come back in somewhere if the
work you're doing matches the
expectations of these levels, which is
really rare. It's like an unusual thing
you'll never hear anyone say, but I've
seen some very rare data points of that.
Um, so if you ever leave the ladder now,
you you kind of created some some leeway
here. Um, but it's it's very rare though
to do something like I think that guy
that went from 5 to 7. He left Google at
5. He joined a startup. He wrote a book
as well on JavaScript and then he came
in at at at Meta as a as a E7 and then
he continued to get promoted. Ricky, uh,
what team are you in at Google? Uh, I'm
in ads. I I describe my job as making
ads pretty. Um, y'all have definitely
seen my ads, even if you've had ad
blocker, I'm sure. Um, maybe maybe
afterwards I'll show you my beautiful
ads. I've seen videos of very like
prolific people in the industry coffing
about how AI is going to be like a low
to midlevel software engineer. Yeah, I
was wondering how like the
implementation of AI and is going to
affect hiring for like entry level.
As far as we see it today, um I think
you know it's hard to say in the future,
maybe in 10 10 years, 5 10 years. In the
short term though, for all of you, even
if you're a first year, I still think
that it's not going to completely change
things. There are still some things that
it's difficult for LMS to do. And if
anything, we just see that LM just
empower engineers. So, um, you know,
it's something that, uh, we use as a
tool and there's a lot of nonAI tools
that we use at work that write code for
us as well and that doesn't scare
anyone. U, this is just like a little
bit further. In conclusion, I don't
think it will majorly change things and
I wouldn't change your strategy. Like,
don't just change major from CS cuz
you're worried that there's not going to
be any jobs. At least for for the people
in this room, if you were maybe a
freshman in high school or something, I
I'm not sure.
Yeah. I think uh my perspective on it is
there are always going to be people who
have to kind of like tell the AI what to
do, right? Tell know the AI has got to
build in this way and then kind of like
verify that it's like correct. So even
though even in like 5 10 years in the
future, I am still imagining right maybe
like an entry-level software engineer,
they're not coding as much because the
AI is going to do it for them, but
they're still kind of like figuring out
how to, you know, get that AI to do what
you want you want it to do. Uh because
AI is always going to be a tool for us,
right? And also people got to build the
AI. Uh so that's kind of my perspective
on things.